A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education, Media, Arts, and Culture (EMAC), Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC), Office Files of John P. Santos FA540
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education, Media, Arts, and Culture (EMAC), Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC), Office Files of John P. Santos
1986-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
Santos, John Phillip
Ford Foundation
FA540
12.26 Cubic Feet About 24 LTR size Hollinger boxes, 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers' papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC, beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
A second set of John P. Santos office files was transferred to the RAC by the Ford Foundation in 2018 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:063. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in October 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Scope and Contents
Collection holds the office files of Ford Foundation Program Officer John Phillip Santos. The files were created during Santos' time in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC).
Collection consists of only one series. It contains the subject and chronological files that Santos and his office created and maintained in order to document his management of Ford Foundation funds for various media related projects as well as his other administrative and program related activities.
Collection is comprised of more than one accession of John P. Santos office files ingested by the RAC over the years. The collection was expanded from 1.3 cubic feet to 10.77 cubic feet in 2018 when a second set of material was transferred, accessioned, and processed. The 2018 accession was added to the end of the original material in the same series in order to reconstitute the relationship between the two groups of records.
The collection principally consists of correspondence, reports, memos, agendas, press clippings, brochures, conference proceedings, Recommended Grant Action reports (RGAs), notes, drafts, and budgets. There is a small amount of audiovisual material within the collection. This material includes a few still images, a VHS tape, an audio CD, and an audio cassette.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 1 series.
The office files in the series appear to consist of two main types of records: subject files and chronological files. However, a Ford Foundation Archives inventory document found in one of the original collection boxes seemed to indicate a close relationship between some of the chronological files and some of the subject files. Within that box, subject files were listed as sub-files to the chronological files. Therefore, it was decided to keep the two types of records together within the series and amend the series title to account for both kinds of documents and the relationship between them.
Although there were some runs of alphabetically organized subject files within the original boxes, this type of scheme was not applied consistently or comprehensively to all of the subject files within the collection. No actions were taken to recapture or impose a total alphabetical arrangement of subject files during processing in 2018. Archivist deferred to the original order of the boxes and the material within the boxes.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject and chronological files, 1986-2002
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
John Phillip Santos worked as a Program Officer in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Ford Foundation's Education, Media, Arts, and Culture (EMAC) Program for six years between 1997 and 2002. In this position, he was responsible for grant making decisions regarding media production through the foundation's Media Projects Fund (MPF). He would review proposals for cultural and educational documentaries, films, media-centered festivals and events, and public broadcasting and television programs. He also focused on emerging technology for media.
Santos is a freelance filmmaker, producer, journalist, and author. Achievements he has made throughout his career include numerous documentaries and news programs he produced for CBS and PBS, articles published in newspapers like the San Antonio News-Express and the New York Times, and service on the President's Advisory Commission on Educational Excellence for Hispanic Americans. He became the first Mexican-American Rhodes Scholar in 1979.
Santos currently serves as a mentor at the Honors College of The University of Texas at San Antonio.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aids concerning the office files of other Ford Foundation officers in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit include:
FA1447 Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Jon Funabiki
Related Materials
A collection containing professional and personal materials created by John Phillip Santos is held at the University of Texas at San Antonio Libraries Special Collections. Some files in the collection specifically regard Santos' work with the Ford Foundation:
John Phillip Santos Papers, MS 203, University of Texas at San Antonio Libraries Special Collections
Ford Foundation; Digital divide; Digital media; Digital television; Documentary films; Film festivals; Independent filmmakers; Journalism; Public broadcasting; Public television
- Subject and chronological files, 1986-2002; 1; 10.77 Cubic Feet About 24 LTR size Hollinger boxes, 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger box
  Scope and Contents
  Series holds the subject and chronological files that John Phillip Santos created during his time as Program Officer in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Ford Foundation's Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC). It consists of more than one accession of Santos' records. The set of records belonging to the first accession of material remains at the beginning of the collection and extends from El Movimiento, 1991, Box 1, Folder 1 to Program Associate - Giraud, Christine, 2000-2001, Box 3, Folder 25. All remaining records in the series originate from the later accession of materials processed in 2018.
  The original accession of records formed an incomplete set of subject files that encouraged the addition of the later accession into the series as a way to repopulate an evident gap in content and reconstitute a relationship between contextually linked documents. The later accession of records revealed a connection between the subject files Santos created and the chronological files he largely used to document his negative responses to proposals for grant funding. Series description was expanded to properly document the association between subject and chronological file.
  Subject files in the series largely regard various media projects and initiatives that the Ford Foundation supported through its Media Projects Fund (MPF) as well as administrative and program planning activities of the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) and its parent Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC). Prominent topics and themes with which Santos dealt in his position as Program Officer for MAC between 1997 and 2002 include the digital transition of public television, education and training for overcoming potential inequalities generated by a digital divide, public support for public television, questions about the role of public television, growing concerns about the integrity of news reporting, and representation of minorities, specifically Latino Americans, within entertainment and news media. Santos appears to have used the term "convenings" to refer to meetings organized at the Ford Foundation for different groups of arts, media, and entertainment professionals such as independent filmmakers and public broadcast grantees. He also created files to document the work of specific Ford Foundation consultants and program associates who assisted his work.
  - El Movimiento, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Islam, etc, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Latino Educational Media Center, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Latino Public Broadcasting, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Leonardo, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Link Media, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Lovett Productions, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Media Channel, 2001 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minority Voices in China's Dayao Mountain District, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Asian American Telecommunications Association (NAATA), 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nalamdana (includes: VHS, Photographs, Cassette Tape), 2000; File includes a set of images. The images have been attached to two sheets of paper. The pictures depict an educational street play and other activities organized by Nalamdana. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Nalamdana Promo / Azhage - Song on HIV/AIDS / Aaadimatham- telefilm on HIV/AIDS, circa2000; VHS; 35 minutes (Box 6, Tape AV 10570)
      Three production on HIV/AIDS: Nalamdana Promo - 7 minutes, English; Azhagig - Song on HIV/AIDS - 4 minutes, Tamil; Aadimatham - Telefilm on HIV/AIDS, 24 minutes, Tamil.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - National Association of Latino Independent Producers (NALIP), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - National Alliance of Media Arts Centers (NAMAC), 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - National Black Programming Consortium, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Council of La Raza (NCLR), 1994-2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Hispanic Foundation for the Arts (NHFA), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Public Radio (NPR), 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - National Video Resources (NVR), 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New York University, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Program Associate - Giraud, Christine, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Chronological file, 1997 April-November (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
    Original folder label said that this chronological file was for April to September 1997, but file actually contains documents from October and November 1997 in the P section.
  - Chronological file, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 29-32)
  - Chronological file, 1998 May-September (Box 4, Folder 33-35)
  - Blackside, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Independents convening, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture Program (MAC) media lab, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Arts in a New Matrix Conference, 1998 September (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Santos Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Trustees presentation, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Video cover copies, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Ashforth, Adam consultant, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Wilson, Diane consultant, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - White House Initiative on Educational Excellence for Hispanic Americans (WHI), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Meeting, Boston, Massachusetts, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Retreat and Reflections Memo, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Draft reserve request - Hopes on the Horizon, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Public Television Initiative for the Digital Age, 1998 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Santos budget projections, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture Program (MAC) visioning retreat - David Sibbett, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Learning Enhancement Foundation-Administered Projects (FAP) consultants, circa 1998 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - New Program Assistants (PAs) - Orientations, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - New computer system, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Independents convening - Notes, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Video Conferencing Task Force, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Second quarter and fourth quarter budget meetings, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Riehl, Dale, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Katzman, Lisa consultant, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Convening of public TV stations, 1998 June 25 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Convening - Independent filmmakers, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Lagos, Nigeria Office Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC) Program Officer candidates, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Program Officer Memo (POM), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Zapata, Angel consultant, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Santos Program Officer Memo (POM) - Drafts and edits, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 64-65)
  - Reflections Memo for Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Retreat, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - International Public Television Screening Conference (INPUT), 1998 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - First quarter meeting, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture Program (MAC) Director interviews, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Workplan, Media Projects Fund (MPF) Fiscal Year 1998, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Media Projects Fund (MPF) projections, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - International Film Financing Conference (IFFCON), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Media and Democracy Congress, 1997; File contains an audio CD titled News Goo. (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - News Goo CD (Box 6, Folder 73)
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Cannes Film Festival, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Camerini-Robertson Documentary Films, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Briefing book: Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) 1999 Worldwide Meeting, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 76-77)
  - United Nations Department of Public Information (UNDP) communications project, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 78-79)
  - Broadcasters - Overseas, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Open University, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 81-83)
  - The Orient Foundation, 1992-1999 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - University of Phoenix, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Mother Jones Magazine, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - National Urban Fellows, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)/Wodiczko, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - University of Mississippi Center for the Study of Southern Culture, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 89-90)
    File contains a piece of correspondence from filmmaker Rory Kennedy that may have been placed in the original folder by accident.
  - Association of Independent Video and Filmmakers (AIVF) kits, 1995-1999 (Box 8, Folder 91-95)
  - Council on Foundations 1998 Film and Video Festival, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 96-98)
  - Santos - Council on Foundations Film Festival Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue/Anna Deavere Smith, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Inroads/Asia, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) planning initiatives, retreats, etc., 1997 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Vector Project, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Video Library, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Committee on Indigenous Peoples (CIP), 1995-1998 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Project Grad, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Los Angeles Task Force, 1992 September 14 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Salary scales, circa 1998 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Staff development, undated (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Worldwide Workshop, Jakarta, Indonesia, 1995-1998 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Arjun Appadurai paper on global philanthropy, 1998 February 16 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Vice Presidents' Initiative Funds, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Cross program learning initiative and travel funds, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Collaborative Funds, 1997 October 28 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Trustees information, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Civic Role of the Arts Study and Advisory Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Press conferences, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Program Assistants, 1997 April 25 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Ford Foundation Asia Offices, 1991-1997 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Ford Foundation Africa Offices, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Ford Foundation Latin America/Caribbean Offices, 1994-1998 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) initiatives, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) initiatives - Innovations in American Government Awards, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) initiatives - The Common Good: Social Welfare and the American Future, 1989 May (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) initiatives - Devolution conference, Michael Lipsky, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) initiatives - Changing Relations Project, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) initiatives, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) initiatives - Conference Board, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR ) initiatives - Religion, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR ) initiatives - Collaborating for educational reform, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR ) initiatives - Crossing Borders, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Fiscal Year 1997 approvals (Box 10, Folder 132)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) U.S. reserves, 1997 October 31 (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - Education, Media, Arts and Culture Program (EMAC) 1997 Annual Programming Review Meeting (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - BOMB Magazine, 1999-2002 (Box 11, Folder 135)
  - Minority media, 1997-2001 (Box 11, Folder 136)
  - Mexican Fine Arts Center Museum, 1997-1999 (Box 11, Folder 137)
  - MIRnet, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 138)
  - Media Projects Fund (MPF), 1988-2000 (Box 11, Folder 139)
  - MTV, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 140)
  - National Community for Latino Leadership (NCLL), 2001 (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - National Association of Hispanic Journalists (NAHJ), 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - National Forum for Public Television Executives (NFPTE), 1998-1999 (Box 12, Folder 143-144)
  - A Woman's Place, 1998-2000 (Box 12, Folder 145-146)
  - Media Policy and Technology Program Officer interviews, 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Corporation for Public Broadcasting Diversity Fund, 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Business Model Project - Digital transition, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 149-150)
  - Digital Divide, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - Arts and Culture Field Discussion - Discussion materials, circa 2000 (Box 13, Folder 152)
  - Transatlantic Information Exchange Service (TIES), 1998 (Box 13, Folder 153)
  - Briefing book: Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) 2000 Worldwide Meeting (Box 13, Folder 154)
  - Literacy, Culture, and Development: Becoming Literate in Morocco by Daniel A. Wagner, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 155)
  - Survivors of the Holocaust study guide, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 156)
  - International Literacy Institute (ILI), 1995-1998 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - Survivors of the Shoah Visual History Foundation, 1996-1997 (Box 13, Folder 158)
  - National Puerto Rican Coalition, Inc (NPRC), undated (Box 13, Folder 159)
  - The Orient Foundation institutional status, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 160)
  - Santos memo on New York documentary, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 161)
  - The Democracy Project on PBS, circa 1998 (Box 13, Folder 162)
  - Transforming Television in India by Sevanti Ninin, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 163)
  - Liberating, Lowbrow and Fun by Shailaja Bhapai, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 164)
  - Connecticut Public Television and Radio 1996 Annual Report, undated (Box 13, Folder 165)
  - New York Times - Why Bold Documentaries Get Few Oscars by Janet Maslin, 1998 March 22 (Box 13, Folder 166)
  - Ford Foundation programming on gay and lesbian issues, 1997-1998 (Box 13, Folder 167)
  - Mediascope, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 168)
  - Community media in India, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 169)
  - Harvard University Graduate School of Education - Project on Humane Creativity, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 170)
  - Du Pont Awards, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - Jodi P. Krizer - Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 172)
  - Platform for Cooperation on Communication and Democratization, undated (Box 14, Folder 173)
  - San Francisco Chronicle - Bay Area's Diverse Voices, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 174)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture Program (MAC) Director interview appointment, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 175)
  - Committee of Concerned Journalists, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - Harvard University Graduate School of Education - Project on Humane Creativity, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - Dana Cunningham - Multi-Foundation Initiative on Race and Difference, 1997 September 5 (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - Syndication Newsfeed Services Directory, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 179)
  - Now What?, 1998 March 9 (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - United States: Adult Literacy and Technology in the United States, by Daniel A. Wagner, undated (Box 14, Folder 181)
  - Kenneth Brecher - Sundance Institute Theatre Laboratory selections, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 182)
  - The Panos Institute - Signposts on the Superhighway: African Environment, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 183)
  - Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) Proceedings: Adult Learning Technology in OECD Countries, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 184)
  - The George Lucas Educational Foundation - Edutopia: Assistive Technology Issue, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 185)
  - TVE International press release, 1998 July 12 (Box 14, Folder 186)
  - Discussion Paper: The Ford Foundation Program in Southern Africa, circa 1998 (Box 14, Folder 187)
  - PostOpinion - Jihad for Kids on PLO-TV, undated (Box 14, Folder 188)